Finding Aid for Louis D. Belcher papers, 1968 and 1976-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Louis D. Belcher papers 1968 and 1976-1985
Belcher, Louis D., 1939-
1 oversize folders
16 linear feet
861004 Aa 2; UAm
Mayor of Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1978-1985. Mayoralty files and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Louis D. Belcher (donor no. 7175 ) in March and April 1985.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Louis D. Belcher was born in Battle Creek, Michigan, on June 25, 1939. He studied industrial engineering at Kellogg Community College and in 1962 took a B.S. in business management from Eastern Michigan University. He served in the Michigan Air National Guard for 14 years (1956-1970).
Belcher dropped out of a management training course at General Motors in 1963, but one year later had become account manager for the National Cash Register Company. He left NCR in 1969, spent two years as business manager and controller for Veda, Inc., and then founded First Ann Arbor Corporation (FAAC). FAAC performs management consulting services and evaluates the design, performance, and testing methods of U.S. combat aircraft. Belcher left FAAC in 1983. He currently (1985) directs two corporations-Environmental Technology, Inc. and Midwest Microwave, Inc.-and owns Data Scan, Inc., Third Party Services, Inc., and a gun shop. He is also a partner in the real estate development firm of Shipman/Corey/Belcher, Inc.
In addition to his success as a businessman, Belcher proved to be a successful local politician as well. A Republican, he was elected to the city council from the fifth ward in 1974 and served until 1978. In 1977 he ran for mayor against incumbent Albert H. Wheeler. The election was disputed, and a special run-off in 1978 gave the office to Belcher. After winning reelection in 1979, 1981, and 1983, Belcher declined to seek a fifth term.
As mayor, Belcher stressed capital improvement projects, business development, reorganizing the city administration, repealing the "$5 marijuana law," expanding the municipal airport, and improving the Ann Arbor Transit Authority's fixed-route service. He pushed through the city's purchase of the Michigan Theater and supported the controversial Tally Hall project. The Ann Arbor News described Belcher as "politically moderate and ardently pro-business, "with a "tendency to shoot from the hip" that was "balanced by political savvy"
This collection of Belcher's papers is confined exclusively to his tenure as mayor of Ann Arbor, 1978-1985. As mayor, Belcher received copies of many of the memos and letters sent to and from the various city departments. Hence this collection represents, to some extent, the records of the city administration as a whole, not just the papers of the mayor. But there are significant gaps in the collection, and some gaps represent major concerns of Belcher's mayoralty. There is virtually no material concerning the Ann Arbor Transit Authority (AATA) or the Housing Commission. (Indeed, of the five principal city commissions, only Planning is represented here.) Most of the city offices and departments have folders in the mayor's files except the Assistant to the City Administrator for Labor Negotiations and Relations, the Data Processing office, and the Bicycle Coordinator of the Transportation Department.
The arrangement of the papers generally reflects their original order. To be sure, in most cases the original order was maintained even though cumbersome and duplicative, because the file system seemed to reflect the priorities, attitudes, and procedures of the mayor's office. When possible the contents list provides cross-references to assist the researcher in overcoming some of the complications of the arrangement. The Belcher mayoralty papers are arranged in seven series: Personal; Official Communications; City Government; Planning File; Conferences, Leagues, and Councils; Topical File; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Mayors--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; City planning--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Municipal government--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Mayors--1977-1985.; Belcher, Louis D., 1939-; Offices--1981-1990.; Mayors--Michigan--Ann Arbor--1977-1985.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal
  Within the Personal series, the Campaign folders contain mostly clippings. However, the 1981 material includes examples of campaign literature and a concession note from Bob Faber, while the 1983 file includes an analysis of the election for the Republican party by Rae Weaver. The Correspondence file is largely composed of letters of congratulations and thanks, and of letters written by school children for class projects. But the subseries also contains letters and cards to and from officials of Ann Arbor's sister cities (Tubigen and Hikone), and some correspondence which could as easily have been filed in the general correspondence file or placed in one of the topical folders.
  - Resumes and Awards circa 1973-1984 (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Campaigns
    - 1981 (Box 1)
      (see also Correspondence, 1981)
    - 1983 (Box 1)
      (see also Correspondence, 1983)
  - Correspondence 1979-1985
    - 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982 (Box 1)
    - 1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Official Communications
  Official Communications is comprised of five subseries: Correspondence and Memos; "While You Were Out" message forms; Proclamations, Commendations, and Press Releases.
  - Correspondence and Memos
    The largest subseries within Official Communications is that of Correspondence and Memos. Particularly noteworthy are Belcher's letters aiding the recruitment of University of Michigan basketball players and the Complaints folders. The range of the complaints is broad and includes poor hiring practices in city hall, juvenile delinquents in Gallup Park, and parking tickets. (Parking tickets seem to be the bane of the city administration's existence, and such letters will also be found in the General correspondence subseries in this series, the Transportation Department subseries of the City Government series, and the Ann Arbor Summer Festival series of the Topical File.)
    - General
      - 1977 (Box 1)
      - 1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1979, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1980 (Box 1)
      - 1981 (Box 1)
      - 1982, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1983 (Box 1)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Letters to Prospective University of Michigan Athletes 1980-1985 (Box 1)
    - Complaints
      (see also Correspondence and Memos, General; also Transportation Department in City Government series)
      - 1978 (Box 2)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
      - 1981-1985 (Box 2)
  - "While You Were Out" Forms (bound)
    Also worthy of mention is the While You Were Out subseries, a set of bound carbons of mostly telephone messages for the mayor. Since the forms often list the purpose of the call or a message from the caller, these books help to fill in the documentary gap normally left by business conducted over the phone.
    - April 10, 1978-October 21, 1978 (Box 2)
    - October 22, 1978-June 26, 1979 (Box 2)
    - June 27, 1979-April 4, 1980 (Box 2)
    - April 4, 1980-October 2, 1980 (Box 2)
    - October 7, 1980-July 27, 1981 (Box 2)
    - July 22, 1981-April 29, 1982 (Box 2)
    - April 28, 1982-January 5, 1983 (Box 2)
    - January 6, 1983-October 18, 1983 (Box 2)
    - October 18, 1983-October 25, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Proclamations
    - 1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980 (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Box 3)
    - 1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983 (Box 3)
    - 1984 (Box 3)
    - 1985 (Box 3)
  - Commendations 1979-1982 (Box 3)
  - Press Releases 1980-1984 (scattered) (Box 3)
- City Government
  Along with the Topical File, the City Government series forms the core of the collection. The series includes a description of the city government's functions and organization ("Your Local Government") which is useful for placing documents in their proper administrative context and for determining the likely place of topical material within the series. Also in the series are city council minutes from January 1982 through December 1983. The Budget and Finance file contains substantive memos, reports, and analyses for some years, as well as detailed printouts of expenditures and allocations. The Planning Commission file contains commission minutes, correspondence, and memos, and should be used in conjunction with the Planning File series. The City Administrator is represented in most of the series and folders in this collection, and most of the material in the file seems to be scattered in duplicates elsewhere. Reports of the disposition of city records, which should be of interest and use to researchers, comprise part of the Central Services and Purchasing file.
  The two largest files are Community Development and Comprehensive Training and Employment. Both represent locally-administered federal government programs. Community Development Block Grants (CDBG) is a U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development project to fund housing rehabilitation and rent subsidies for low-income persons, street and park improvements, legal aid, and health care services. Several folders in the Topical File are cross-referenced to the Community Development series. The Labor Department's Comprehensive Employment and Training Act (CETA) is responsible for improving delivery of employment services, including counseling and training.
  The Fifteenth District Court file is almost entirely made up of letters to and from Senior Judge S. J. Elden. Complaints against and praise for police officers are located in the Police Department file, along with a fiscal report and crime statistics. The Transportation Department has authority over parking enforcement, traffic engineering, and the Municipal Airport. The bulk of the material on the airport controversy will be found in the transportation department's file, but some is also located in the Planning File. The bulk of parking ticket complaints is also lodged in this file. Material on drains, sewers, and flooding will be found in the Utilities Department file.
  - General
    - "Your Local Government" (Box 3)
    - Appointments
      (see also GOP in Topical File)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 3)
      - 1978 (Box 3)
      - 1979 (Box 3)
  - City Council
    - General
      - "Rules of the Council," undated (Box 3)
      - Council File 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - Minutes
      - January-April, 1982 (Box 3)
      - May-August, 1982 (Box 3)
      - September-December, 1982 (Box 3)
      - January-April, 1983 (Box 3)
      - May-August, 1983 (Box 3)
      - September-December, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Budget and Finance
    (see also Taxes in Topical File)
    - Budgets
      - 1978-1979 (Box 4)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 4)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 4)
      - 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1982-1983, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 4)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - Capital Improvements Budget Programs 1981-1986, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Annual Financial Report 1982 (Box 4)
    - Bond Proposals for Building Authority 1981 (Box 4)
    - Executive Pay Plan 1979-1986 (Box 4)
    - Total Operations Management System 1983 (Box 4)
  - Planning Commission
    (see also Planning File series)
    - 1980 (Box 4)
    - 1981 (Box 5)
    - 1982 (Box 5)
    - 1983 (Box 5)
    - 1984 (Box 5)
  - Administrator (City)
    - Search for (Korn and Feory Consultants),1979-1980
      - 1981 (Box 5)
      - 1982 (Box 5)
      - 1983 (Box 5)
      - 1984 (Box 5)
    - General Revenue Sharing Plan 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Personal File, Terry Sprenkel 1979-1984 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - Assessor (City) 1979-1984 (Box 5)
  - Attorney (City)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 5)
  - Building Department
    - General 1983-1985 (Box 5)
    - U-Haul Case 1982 (Box 5)
  - Central Services and Purchasing
    - General 1978-1983 (Box 5)
    - Transmittal of City Records to Records Center 1967-1983 (Box 5)
  - Clerk (City)
    - General 1978-1983 (Box 5)
    - Redistribution and Reapportionment 1981-1982 (Box 5)
      (see also Reapportionment in Topical File)
  - Community Development
    (see also Tally Hall in Planning File; also scan Topical File for various cross references)
    - General
      - 1978-1979, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1980 (Box 5)
      - 1981, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1982 (Box 6)
      - 1983 (Box 6)
      - 1984 (Box 6)
    - Subject
      - Dental Clinic 1979-1983 (Box 6)
      - Energy Conservation Program 1978-1983, 2 folders (Box 6)
        (see also Hydroelectric Project in Planning File)
      - Home Repair 1978-1982 (Box 6)
      - Housing and Energy Assistance Plans 1978-1982 (Box 6)
      - Model Cities Health and Legal Clinics Dispute 1980-1982, 2 folders (Box 6)
        (see also Topical File: North Central Property Owners Association, Inc.)
      - Monitoring Visits 1978-1979 (Box 6)
      - Relocation Assistance 1976 (Box 6)
      - Senior and Section 8 Housing 1978-1984 (Box 6)
      - Senior Transportation 1982-1984 (Box 6)
  - Comprehensive Employment and Training (CETA)
    (see also Topical File: U.S. Government, Department of Labor)
    - 1979 (Box 6)
    - 1980 (Box 6)
    - 1981 (Box 6)
    - 1982 (Box 7)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 7)
  - Controller (city) 1980-1984 (Box 7)
  - Disaster Preparedness, Office of
    - 1978-1980 (Box 7)
    - 1981-1984 (Box 7)
  - District Court, Fifteenth
    - General 1978-1983 (Box 7)
    - Judges' Salaries 1981 (Box 7)
  - Engineering Department
    (see also Sister Lakes Drain in Topical File)
    - General
      - 1979-1981 (Box 7)
      - 1982-1985 (Box 7)
    - Sidewalk Repair Program 1980-1984 (Box 7)
  - Fire Department
    - General 1979-1984 (Box 7)
    - Act 289 1980-1983 (Box 7)
  - Municipal Garage 1979-1984 (Box 7)
  - Parks and Recreation Department
    - 1978
      - General (Box 7)
      - Proposed Parks and Open Space Plan (Box 7)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 7)
    - 1983 (Box 7)
    - 1984 (Box 7)
    - Parks Millage Proposal 1982-1983 (Box 7)
  - Personnel/Human Rights Department 1978-1985, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Police Department
    - 1978-1979 (Box 7)
    - 1980 Selection of a chief (Box 7)
    - 1983 (Box 7)
    - 1984 (Box 7)
  - Solid Waste Department
    - General 1980-1984 (Box 7)
    - Shredder Proposal 1979-1980 (Box 8)
    - Landfill 1978-1980 (Box 8)
  - Transportation Department
    - Streets, Traffic, and Parking
      (see also Planning File)
      - Carpool Program 1979 (Box 8)
      - Iroquois Street 1978-1979 (Box 8)
      - Parking Complaints 1980-1985 (Box 8)
        (see also Complaints in Official Communications series)
      - Snow Removal 1979-1985 (Box 8)
        (includes material relating to parking)
      - Miscellaneous 1983-1984 (Box 8)
    - Airport
      - 1975-Expansion
        - Correspondence
          - Pros (Box 8)
          - Con (Box 8)
        - Public Hearing (Box 8)
        - General (Box 8)
      - 1976 (Box 8)
      - 1978 (Box 8)
      - 1979, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 8)
      - 1983, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Treasurer (City) 1980-1984 (scattered) (Box 8)
  - Utilities Department
    - General 1983-1984 (Box 8)
    - Drains, Sewers, and Flooding
      (see also Sister Lakes Drain and Water Quality Management Plan in Topical File)
      - General 1975-1979 (Box 9)
      - Storm water Management Plans, Fee System Proposal, Hydrologic Analysis 1983 (Box 9)
    - Wastewater Treatment Plant 1978-1983 (Box 9)
- Planning File (see also Planning Commission in City Government series)
  The purpose of Planning File series is somewhat obscure, since the mayor's staff placed much related material in the Topical File. One possible purpose of the file was to highlight development projects and area plans, and probably reflects Belcher's great interest in such propositions. Along with correspondence, the series includes developers' promotional brochures, site plans, and other visual representations. There are extensive cross-references from this series to others.
  - Ace Hardware Rezoning and Site Plan 1979 (Box 9)
  - Airport Expansion 1982-1984 (Box 9)
    (see also City Government series, Transportation Department)
  - Ann Arbor Inn 1981-1982 (Box 9)
  - Arborland Shopping Center 1975-1983 (includes analysis of traffic flow) (Box 9)
  - Arrowwood Hills (Box 9)
    (see Topical File; also see City Government: Community Development)
  - Barton Ponds-Boat Launch 1980-1984, 2 folders (Box 9)
    (see also Topical File: Michigan Rowing Association)
  - Berger Developments (Riverside, Huron Plaza, etc.) 1979-1982 (Box 9)
  - Black Pond Development 1980-1981 (Box 9)
  - Brauer Site Plan 1981 (Box 9)
  - Briarwood Mall Apartments 1979-1983 (Box 9)
  - Chizek Rezoning 1978-1980 (Box 9)
  - Cranbrook Village Development 1979-1982 (Box 9)
  - Crematoriums 1979-1980 (Box 9)
  - Edmund Place Condominiums 1980 (Box 9)
  - Foxfire 1979-1981 (Box 9)
  - Fuller-Geddes/Fuller-Glen Roads Project 1979-1981 (Box 9)
  - Green/Baxter Park 1979 (Box 9)
  - Greenbelt 1979-1980 (Box 9)
  - Hoffman (Orchard Professional Building Rezoning) Project 1980 (Box 9)
  - Hoover Mansion 1982-1983 (Box 9)
  - Huron Plaza 1980-1983 (Box 9)
  - Hydroelectric Project at City (Huron River) Dams 1979-1984 (Box 9)
    (see also City Government: Community Development, Energy Conservation Program)
  - Ingalls Street Vacation Planning 1979 (Box 9)
  - John Knox Senior Citizen Village (Box 9)
    (see Topical File)
  - Johnson-Greene Property 1982 (Box 9)
  - Kambly Property (1700 Broadway) 1983 (Box 9)
    (see also Halfway House in Topical File)
  - Kimberly Hills (Packard-Gladstone/Dion Property Development) 1978-1980 (Box 10)
  - Leslie Laboratories (Box 10)
  - Liberty Knolls Development 1980-1982 (Box 10)
    (see also City Government: Utilities Department)
  - Lokey (Classy Chassis Car Wash) Site 1980 (Box 10)
  - Marshall Park Property 1982-1983 (Box 10)
  - Mercedes Benz Industrial Development Revenue Bonds 1979-1981 (Box 10)
  - North Central Property Owners Association. (Box 10)
  - Old Westside (Box 10)
  - Old YMCA Building 1979-1982 (Box 10)
  - Packard-Beakes Property 1976-1981 (Box 10)
  - Packard/Main Senior Citizen Housing 1978-1980 (Box 10)
  - Parking Structures 1978-1983 (Box 10)
  - Parkway Meadows 1978-1980 (Box 10)
  - Pittsfield Valley Farms 1978-1981 (Box 10)
  - Platt/I-94 Interchange 1979-1980 (Box 10)
  - Plymouth Professional Park 1979-1980 (Box 10)
  - Quadrium One 1979-1980 (Box 10)
  - Railroads (including new Amtrak station) 1979-1984 (Box 10)
  - St. Joseph's Hospital/Catherine McAuley Health Center 1980-1984 (Box 10)
  - Second Baptist Church 1980 (Box 10)
  - Senior Housing Co-op (Box 10)
  - State Street Area Improvements (Box 10)
  - Southside State Street Improvements (Box 10)
  - Sunset Woods (includes draft of Belcher remarks in City Council) 1977-1978 (Box 10)
  - Tally Hall 1983 (Box 10)
    (see also City Government: Community Development)
  - Traver Lakes 1978-1979 (Box 10)
  - Thayer Memorial Fountain Plaza 1979 (Box 10)
  - University Hospitals (including Burn Center) 1978-1984 (Box 10)
  - Warner Lambert-Parke Davis 1982-1983 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Annexations (Box 10)
    - Area Plans (Box 10)
    - Lot Splits (Box 10)
    - Rezonings (Box 10)
    - Site Plans (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
- Conferences, Leagues, and Councils
  Minutes, newsletters, memos, correspondence, and committee material relating to the various municipal and mayoralty organizations of which Ann Arbor and Belcher were members comprise the Conferences, Leagues, and Councils series. Belcher served on the board of directors and as president (1983-1985) of the Michigan Conference of Mayors. His actual degree of involvement in the other organizations is difficult to determine from the documents found here.
  - Michigan Conference of Mayors 1982-1984
    - Minutes and Bylaws (Box 11)
    - Summer Workshops and Newsletters (Box 11)
  - Michigan Municipal League
    - General 1980-1983 (Box 11)
    - Legislative and Urban Affairs Committee 1980-1983 (Box 11)
    - Energy Committee 1983 (Box 11)
  - National Conference of Republican Mayors 1981 (Box 11)
  - National League of Cities
    - General 1979-1983 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Finance, Administration, and Inter-governmental Relations 1979-1984 (Box 11)
    - Congress of Cities 1982 (Box 11)
  - Southeast Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG)
    - General
      - 1977-1978 (Box 11)
      - 1979 (includes 1976 material) (Box 11)
      - 1980-1985 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Criminal Justice
      - 1979 (Box 11)
      - 1980 (Box 11)
      - 1981 (Box 11)
    - Law Enforcement Assistance Administration 1980-1981 (Box 11)
  - U.S. Conference of Mayors
    - 1979 (Box 11)
    - 1980 (Box 11)
    - 1981, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 11)
    - 1984 (Box 11)
    - City Livability Award 1984 (Box 11)
- Topical File
  Along with the City Government series, the Topical File series forms the core of this collection. The topical series contains correspondence and memos about the issues, places, events, and organizations represented. The file also incorporates ephemera such as brochures, programs, and meeting announcements, and more substantial documents such as minutes, reports, and financial statements.
  To highlight the series accurately might run several pages, so only three examples are provided for illustrative purposes. The (Ann Arbor) Civic Theatre folder contains notices of the AACT's advisory council meetings, clippings, and proposals for fundraising and for using the old city firehouse for the theatre's headquarters. The GOP file contains agendas and minutes for Ann Arbor's party caucuses, a 1980 list of local party activists, and extensive material on the annual Concord Conferences. The conferences are workshops for Republican politicians from throughout the country, and the 1978 session featured an analysis of Belcher's campaign against Wheeler. The Halfway House folder documents the controversy surrounding a state proposal to open a correctional facility at 1700 Broadway; material includes citizen letters, the city administrator's statement at the public hearing, and a couple of letters to the mayor from the governor.
  - Alcoholism, Washtenaw County Council on 1982-1983 (Box 11)
  - All-American City 1982 (Box 11)
  - American Friends Service Committee 1983 (Box 11)
  - Ann Arbor Area Foundation 1975-1984 (includes minutes) (Box 11)
  - Ann Arbor Chamber Orchestra 1979-1982 (Box 11)
  - Ann Arbor Boxing Club 1980-1983 (Box 11)
  - Ann Arbor Public Schools
    (see also Correspondence in Personal series)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 12)
    - 1981-1984 (Box 12)
  - Ann Arbor Summer Festival
    - Memos, Progress Reports, and Miscellaneous
      - 1978-1979 (Box 12)
      - 1980-1984, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Minutes 1979-1984, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Finances 1979-1983 (Box 12)
    - Clippings and Flyers (Box 12)
  - Ann Arbor Township 1980-1984 (Box 12)
  - Arbor Haven Emergency Shells 1980-1982 (Box 12)
  - Arrowwood Hills Co-op 1980-1984 (Box 12)
    (see also U.S. Government: Department of HEW in this series; also Community Development in City Government series)
  - Art Fair
    - General 1978-1984 (Box 12)
    - Parking and Street Closings (including complaints) 1980-1982 (Box 12)
      (see also Transportation Department in City Government series)
  - Arts 1980-1982 (Box 12)
  - A, Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Blacktown, Australia 1979-1980 (Box 12)
  - Casualty Insurance (for City) 1979 (Box 12)
  - Center for Occupational and Personalized Education, Inc. (Box 12)
    (see COPE; also see Community Development in City Government series)
  - Census 1980-1984 (Box 12)